{"tossups": [{"question": "Thomas Chittenden was the first governor of this state, once known as The Republic of New Connecticut. At first, this state was governed from the town of Windsor, before its capital moved to its present location in 1805. This state was briefly an independent country from 1777 to 1791, and during the Revolutionary War, the Green Mountain Boys were considered part of the militia from this colony. For ten points, name this New England state, today led from Montpelier.", "answer": "<b><u>Vermont</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During the early years of this route\u2019s existence, ice-breaking ferries like the SS <em>Angara</em> provided a linkage over a large lake. In the early years of World War Two, this route was used to transport natural rubber from Southeast Asia to Europe, and Kurt G\u00f6del [[GUR-duhl]] and Bette Erlich Lowenstein took this transportation line during their escape from Nazi Germany. The Circum-Baikal Railway was once part of, for ten points, what rail line that runs from Vladivostok to Moscow?", "answer": "<b><u>Trans-Siberian</u></b> Railway (prompt on \u201cTSR\u201d)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "A set of policies introduced by this leader led to the Thirty Glorious Years, an economic boom following World War Two. During the Empty Chair Crisis, this person ordered a withdrawal from the European Economic Community. This leader was targeted by a student uprising in May of 1968, during which his eventual successor, Georges Pompidou, negotiated on his behalf. The first president of the Fifth Republic was, for ten points, what leader of France during World War Two?", "answer": "Charles <b><u>de Gaulle</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Marian Anderson performed in this type of work only once, appearing as Ulrica. Marietta Alboni often played \u201cbreeches roles\u201d in works of this type, whereas Adelina Patti played <em>coloratura</em> roles. Leontyne Price, an African-American performer in this genre, was advised to not make her debut in the stereotypical slave role of Aida, instead debuting as Leonora in <em>Il Trovatore</em>. For ten points, name this form of theatre, in which Camilla Williams performed as Mimi, Bess, and Madama Butterfly.", "answer": "<b><u>Opera</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "In 1645, during this region\u2019s Civil War, Fran\u00e7oise-Marie Jacquelin assumed command of the garrison at Fort la Tour while her husband, Governor Charles de Saint-\u00c9tienne de la Tour, was in Boston seeking support for their cause. The Wabanaki Confederacy maintained control of part of this region, northeast of the Kennebec River in Maine, during King Philip's War. For ten points, name this colony of New France which gives its name to a US National Park near Bar Harbor, Maine.", "answer": "<b><u>Acadia</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Chief Justice John Rutledge once served as governor of this state, where Patrick Ferguson was killed by Patriot militia at the Battle of Kings Mountain. Francis Marion, the \u201cSwamp Fox,\u201d led guerilla forces in this state. Horatio Gates was fired for losing the Battle of Camden in this state, though American forces later decisively defeated the British at the Battle of Cowpens. For ten points, name this Southern US state where the British captured the city of Charleston.", "answer": "<b><u>South Carolina</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Following this event, the Rogers Commission was appointed to investigate its cause. Members of that commission included Chuck Yeager, Neil Armstrong, and Richard Feynman, who demonstrated, during a televised hearing before Congress, how defective O-rings caused this event. In an emotional speech about this event, Ronald Reagan quoted the poem \u201cHigh Flight.\u201d For ten points, what space shuttle disaster claimed the lives of seven astronauts, including Christa McAuliffe?", "answer": "<em><b><u>Challenger</u></b></em> disaster", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The first leader of this organization, former Treasury Secretary Thomas Ewing, Sr., served in that role under Zachary Taylor and Millard Filmore. In 1983, the leader of this department, James G. Watt, banned the Beach Boys and the Grass Roots from playing Independence Day concerts on the National Mall. If she is confirmed by the Senate, New Mexico congresswoman and Laguna Pueblo member Deb Haaland will become the first Native American to lead, for ten points, what executive department in charge of managing federal lands?", "answer": "United States Department of the <b><u>Interior</u></b> (prompt on \u201cDOI\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This team played on Huntington Avenue before moving to its current stadium in 1912 and was a crosstown rival of the Braves until 1952. This team has had three Triple Crown winners, including one player who did it in both 1952 and 1957. In 2005 this team hired baseball\u2019s youngest General Manager, Theo Epstein. For ten points, Steve Pearce, Johnny Damon, and Babe Ruth helped what New York Yankees rival win three of their nine titles, including the first World Series in 1903 when they were simply named \u201cthe Americans\u201d?", "answer": "<b><u>Boston Red Sox</u></b> (accept either <b><u>Boston</u></b> or <b><u>Red Sox</u></b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A song about this movement compares its semi-fictional founder to Robin Hood, saying the founder is \u201cnow the Hero of Nottinghamshire.\u201d A group of these people ambushed mill owner William Horsfall, leading to a well-covered 19th century news story about the following trial and execution at York Castle. England criminalized one of this political entity\u2019s main tactics via the \u201cFrame Breaking Act\u201d in 1812. For ten points, name this group of specialized textile workers whose name is synonymous with any person resistant to technological change.", "answer": "<b><u>Luddite</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Derry Coburn often accompanied this man in his later life, and William Russell and this man led an expedition during which they had a meeting at Sycamore Shoals with Richard Henderson. Blackfish took this man to Chillicothe after he was forced to run the gauntlet. This man is often depicted atop Pilot Knob looking at the Bluegrass Region. This longhunter served under Hugh Waddell to suppress the Cherokee uprising. For ten points, name this folk hero who blazed the Wilderness Road into Kentucky.", "answer": "Daniel <b><u>Boone</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During this period, the May Report advocated for expenditure cuts, and the Left Book Club produced monthly warnings during this period. Hunger marches in this era included one by ship workers from Jarrow. Oswald Mosely advocated for greater pensions and control over banks in this period before founding his own Fascist Party. After a mutiny, the gold standard was abandoned by England during this period. For ten points, name this period of economic decline that began after a crash on Wall Street.", "answer": "Great <b><u>Depression</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "French chemist Hippolyte M\u00e8ge-Mouri\u00e8s made the first instance of this food after experimenting with a fatty acid discovered by Michel Eugene Chevreul and named for pearls. Henry Bradley patented a process to make this food from cottonseed oil rather than beef fat. Historically, New York and New Jersey forced this food to be colored pink instead of yellow as part of a color ban. For ten points, name this food whose creation stemmed from a challenge set forth by Napoleon III to furnish the military with a butter substitute.", "answer": "<b><u>Margarine</u></b> (accept <b><u>Oleo</u></b>; accept <b><u>Oleomargarine</u></b>, prompt on \"Marge\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Paul Coe helped found a legal service for these people in 1970. Stockmen and house servants from these people participated in the Wave Hill walk-off. The doctrine of \"terra nullius\" was replaced with the right of \"native title\" for these people in <em>Mabo v. Queensland</em>. Many of these people hold to The Dreaming, and Uluru is sacred to those known as the Alangu among these people. Torres Strait islanders are generally considered distinct from, for ten points, which people from places like Tasmania and the Outback?", "answer": "<b><u>Aboriginal Australians</u></b> (accept answers including <b><u>Aborigines</u></b> and <b><u>Australia</u></b>, prompt on \"Aborigines\" alone, prompt on \"Indigenous Australians\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "According to Werner Sombart, a period named for this material formed during the pre-industrial phase. Shortages of this material are noted in German history as the <em>Holznot</em>, and Joachim Radkau\u2019s history of this material claims that fear of a lack of this material led to modern environmentalism. Huge rafts of this material were sent to the Netherlands for shipbuilding after having been extracted from the Black Forest. For ten points, excessive use of what material in Germany caused deforestation?", "answer": "<b><u>Wood</u></b> (accept <b><u>Trees</u></b>, <b><u>Timber</u></b>, and other similar answers relating to <b><u>wood</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This structure was criticized in a leaflet titled \"Public Necessity or Just Plain Pork\". Luther Ely Smith proposed this structure to Mayor Bernard Dickmann, which led to the creation of the non-profit \"Jenny May.\u201d In 1934, John Cochran and Bennett Champ Clark introduced an appropriation bill to create this structure which is situated near the Old Courthouse where the Dred Scott decision took place. Eero Saarinen designed this stainless steel monument that overlooks the Mississippi River. For ten points, name this St. Louis arch.", "answer": "<b><u>Gateway</u></b> Arch (or <b><u>Gateway</u></b> to the West; accept <b><u>St. Louis Arch</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Judge John G. Davies criticized this man, who invested in Straight Alta-Pazz Records. A George Holliday film shows this man being attacked while with Bryant Allen and Freddie Helms, after which this man wrote <em>The Riot Within</em>. Tim and Melanie Singer first encountered this man on the highway, and Daryl Gates said excessive force was used on this man. This man was quoted saying, \"Can we all just get along?\" For ten points, name this man who was beaten by the LAPD in 1991 causing citywide riots.", "answer": "Rodney <b><u>King</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A treasure named for one of these features includes The Muse Casket and Projecta Casket. Pallantium settlers name one of these natural features, and the entire population of Alba Longa was resettled in one of these places possibly named for \"heaven.\u201d One of these natural features contains the Baths of Constantine and the Horse Tamers statues as well as the presidential Quirinal Palace. The Esquiline, Palatine and Aventine are three of these features. For ten points, what are these raised areas, seven of which are core to the city of Rome?", "answer": "Seven <b><u>Hill</u></b>s of Rome", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "Ocean the Jesup Expedition explored off the coast of British Columbia.", "answer": "<b><u>Pacific</u></b> Ocean", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Expedition across the Louisiana Purchase also called the Corps of Discovery.", "answer": "<b><u>Lewis and Clark</u></b> Expedition (accept <b><u>Corps of Discovery</u></b> if answer before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Country that ceded Pacific Northwest Claims to the US in the Adams-On\u00eds Treaty.", "answer": "<b><u>Spain</u></b> (accept <b><u>Spanish</u></b> Empire)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "President who ordered the Corps of Discovery expedition.", "answer": "Thomas <b><u>Jefferson</u> </b>  Highly predictable feature discovered by the 1870 Washburn-Langford-Doane (5)  Expedition in Wyoming.  ANSWER: <b><u>Old Faithful</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Russian Peninsula explored by Vitus Bering before coming to North America.", "answer": "<b><u>Kamchatka</u> </b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Geologist whose expedition was the first US government-sponsored passage through the Grand Canyon.", "answer": "John Wesley <b><u>Powell</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Rail magnate who headed Union Pacific and led the 1899 scientific expedition to Alaska.", "answer": "E(dward) H. <b><u>Harriman</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Northern European region from which the Vikings came, including Norway and Sweden.", "answer": "<b><u>Scandinavia</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Hammer-wielding god who names the day before Friday.", "answer": "<b><u>Thor</u> </b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Germanic alphabet that included the Elder and Younger Futhark.", "answer": "<b><u>Runes</u></b> (or <b><u>Runic</u></b> alphabet)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Region Rollo settled in France, where William the Conqueror was duke before being king of England.", "answer": "<b><u>Normandy</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "North American coastal area visited by Leif Erikson that is named for its grapes.", "answer": "<b><u>Vinland</u> </b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Byzantine guard created under Basil II, whose members included Harald Hardrada.", "answer": "<b><u>Varangian</u></b> Guard", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Norse site in Newfoundland found in 1960.", "answer": "<b><u>L'Anse aux Meadows</u> </b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Celtic Holy Island that Saints Aidan and Cuthbert governed before the Vikings sacked it.", "answer": "Holy island of <b><u>Lindisfarne</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Co-capital with Sucre since 1898.", "answer": "<b><u>La Paz</u> </b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Bordering Andean nation with which Bolivia united in 1836, angering Chile and Argentina.", "answer": "<b><u>Peru</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "War which led to Bolivia losing access to the title ocean.", "answer": "War of the <b><u>Pacific</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "President who fled in 2019 at the request of the military due to electoral irregularities.", "answer": "Evo <b><u>Morales</u> </b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Oil company owned by Brazil which had its facilities occupied by government forces.", "answer": "<b><u>Petrobras</u></b> (accept <b><u>Petr\u00f3leo Brasiliero</u></b> S.A.; accept <b><u>Brazilian Petroleum</u> </b>Corporation)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Silver mining hub of Colonial Spain, an Andean city in Central Bolivia.", "answer": "<b><u>Potos\u00ed</u> </b>  Left-wing politician who was elected president in 2020. (7)  ANSWER: Luis \"Lucho\" <b><u>Arce</u> </b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Aymara peasant who led a 1781 revolt and remains a hero for many indigenous people.", "answer": "Tupac <b><u>Katari</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>According to</u> </b><em><b><u>South Dakota v. Dole</u></b></em><b><u>, it is constitutional to withhold federal</u></b> <b><u>funding for these structures in locations where the drinking age is under 21. One of</u></b> <b><u>these structures in Lower Manhattan, proposed by Robert Moses, was never built due</u></b> <b><u>to protests by activists like Jane (+)</u> Jacobs. Congress\u2019s 1956 bill to fund more of these structures contributed to \"white flight.\" After studying the (*) </b><em>Autobahn</em>, Dwight Eisenhower backed the creation of, for ten points, what high-speed roads?", "answer": "<b><u>Highway</u></b>s (or <b><u>Freeway</u></b>s; or <b><u>Interstate</u></b>(s) Highway System, prompt on \u201croads\u201d and similar answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 1296, this man, whose nickname was \u201cMilione\u201d [[meel-YONE-eh]] was</u></b> <b><u>captured during a war with Genoa. While in prison, this man's cellmate was the</u></b> <b><u>author of</u> </b><em><b><u>Romance of King Arthur</u></b></em><b><u>, a Pisan known as Rusticiano. Historians have</u></b> <b><u>accused this man of (+)</u> exaggeration in stories such as having accompanied Princess Kokochin to Persia. This Italian was welcomed at the court of Kublai (*) </b>Khan, and later provided Europeans with their first in-depth information about Far Eastern culture. For ten points, name this Venetian explorer, namesake of a swimming pool game.", "answer": "Marco <b><u>Polo</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>HGV driver Stewart Dimmock sued over the distribution of this film. Michael</u></b> <b><u>Brook included songs like \"Prof. Revelle\" on this film's soundtrack. The sequel to this</u></b> <b><u>film,</u> </b><em><b><u>Truth to Power</u></b></em><b><u>, was released a year after the signing of the 2016 (+)</u> Paris Agreement. MIT atmospheric theorist Richard Lindzen criticized this movie as politically biased. Laurie David invited a previous Vice (*) </b>President to take part in this film, which features ice core data presented in a keynote style. For ten points, name this 2006 film featuring Al Gore on global warming.", "answer": "<em><b><u>An Inconvenient Truth</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>A leader of this state issued the \"kvindefred\" ordinance and expanded the</u></b> <b><u>Brigittine Language. Henry IV's daughter, Philippa of Lancaster, married into this</u></b> <b><u>state. A founder of this state was called \"King Breechless\" and \"Semiramis of the</u></b> <b><u>North\u201d and was succeeded by (+)</u> Bogislav. This state faced the Engelbrekt rebellion against its leader Eric of Pomerania. At the Treaty of Malmo, this transnational state lost (*) </b>Sweden, a result of Gustav Vasa's successful capture of Stockholm. Queen Margaret led, for ten points, what Scandinavian Union?", "answer": "<b><u>Kalmar</u></b> Union", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Early Navajo works of this type often used cochineal [[KOTCH-ih-NEEL]] and rabbit bush to add color to geometric designs such as Eye Dazzler and Diamond Twill. <em>Kilim</em> were works of this type created in the Persian empire, and featured motifs meant to bring luck and ward off evil. The <em>kesi</em> technique of creating these works uses short weft threads to create colorful images visible on both sides of the finished piece. For ten points, name this type of weaving, commonly made from wool or silk, which results in detailed images that are often hung on walls.", "answer": "<b><u>Tapestry</u></b> (prompt on \u201cweaving,\u201d \u201cwoven,\u201d \u201cfabric,\u201d \u201ctextiles,\u201d and similar answers; accept [a]Carpet/a] or similar floor-coverings such as \"Rug\" prior to \"Kesi\")", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>This city's Municipal Police opposed the Metropolitan Police after the</u></b> <b><u>appointment of Charles Devlin as City Street Commissioner by Mayor Fernando</u></b> <b><u>Wood. In another incident in this city, supporters of actor Edwin Forrest fought fans</u></b> <b><u>of William Charles Macready in the (+)</u> Astor Place Riot. In 1863, working-class Irishmen in this city burned down the Colored Orphan Asylum while protesting the (*) </b>Conscription Act. For ten points, what city endured civil war draft riots along Third Avenue, as well as protests against Tammany Hall?", "answer": "<b><u>New York</u></b> City (accept <b><u>NYC</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The construction of this river's Lower Monumental Dam in 1968 caused the</u></b> <b><u>Marmes Rockshelter, one of the best-preserved Native American archaeological sites</u></b> <b><u>along this river, to permanently flood. In 1893, the steamship</u> </b><em><b><u>Annie Faxon</u></b></em><b><u> sank on</u></b> <b><u>this river while transporting copper ore from (+)</u> Hells Canyon to Lewiston. In 1805, Lewis and Clark traversed the modern state of Idaho in dugout canoes along the (*) </b>Clearwater, this river\u2019s largest tributary. For ten points, name this river of the Pacific Northwest, whose headwaters begin at Yellowstone National Park.", "answer": "<b><u>Snake</u></b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>Daniel Williams and Glenn Foard helped identify this battle's location, which</u></b> <b><u>is contested by Peter Foss's \"Redemore\" theory. The blind historian Bernard Andr\u00e9</u></b> <b><u>was so overwhelmed by this battle's importance that he left a blank page for it in his</u></b> <b><u>opus. The Duke of (+)</u> Norfolk may have died at this battle near the Dadlington windmill, and Richard Ratcliffe was killed at this battle at which the Stanleys joined the winners. Henry (*) </b>VII defeated Richard III in, for ten points, what closing battle of the Wars of the Roses?", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Bosworth</u></b> Field", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Ambrose Schilizzi claimed to find this man's mummy in the Nabi Daniel</u></b> <b><u>Mosque. A sarcophagus once thought to be that of this man actually belonged to</u></b> <b><u>Abdalonymus. Augustus placed a golden diadem on this man, and this man's</u></b> <b><u>breastplate was taken by Caligula while (+)</u> Caracalla removed his tunic. While on a funerary cart, this man's body was stolen in Syria by Ptolemy I Soter and brought to Memphis. This man died in (*) </b>Babylon after a life of conquest during which he won at Issus and reached India. For ten points, name this Macedonian conqueror.", "answer": "<b><u>Alexander</u></b> the Great (or <b><u>Alexander</u></b> III of Macedon)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}